Guide to the Geneva Valentine papers, 1922-2008 MS2340
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Geneva Valentine papers
circa 1920s to circa 2008
1922-1987
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Valentine, Hugh, Jr.
Valentine, Geneva Kent
MS2340
16 Linear Feet
This collection contains correspondence, personal writing, publications, legal and financial documents, memoranda, meeting minutes, memorabilia, photographs, scrapbooks, negatives, yearbooks, and company records documenting the activities of businesswoman, realtor, and Washington DC community leader Geneva K. Valentine. These materials date from 1922 to 2008 since they include records of family members and family-run corporations in addition to the records of Mrs. Valentine. The bulk of the collection dates between 1922 and 1987.
Biographical / Historical
Geneva Kent Valentine (1901-1971), a prominent businesswoman and community leader in Washington, DC, was the first African-American to gain membership in the National Association of Real Estate Boards, among many other achievements. Mrs. Valentine was born in Northumberland County, Virginia on August 15, 1901. She graduated from Washington DC's Dunbar High School in 1922, and graduated from Hartshorn Memorial College's Normal School in Richmond, Virginia before attending law school at American Uniersity. Mrs. Valentine worked as a secretary before going into business. She was president of Equitable Realty Co. (which she helped found in 1931) and managed several other companies in addition to her real estate career, including the first Western Union branch on the east coast to be owned by an African-American.
Mrs. Valentine was well-known as a civic leader in professional clubs and local organizations who demonstrated significant involvement in causes related to education, housing, and urban poverty. She served as National President of the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs and was a member of the Century Club. She contributed to community initiatives as President of the Adams-Morgan Federation and an organizer of Positive Action Against Crime, as well as through the events and services she helped provide at Inspiration House (a black cultural center), the Guy T.O. Hollyday House (a community revitalization and redevelopment organization), and her work on education and library resources through the M.C. Terrell Fund. She also worked with the Mayor's Economic Development Committee on initiatives to foster police-community relations.
Mrs. Valentine was highly involved in Civil Rights movements through the Leadership Conference on Civil Rights and her efforts as Legislative Chairman of the national Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs. Her opinions have been solicited regarding Civil Rights legislation, and the organizations with which she was involved prepared reports and commentaries on these issues. Mrs. Valentine was a registered Republican and served as Chairman of the Assembly of Women's Organizations for National Security. She has corresponded with Civil Rights activist A. Philip Randolph, DC's Mayor Walter E. Washington, U.S. Senators including Edward Kennedy and Gaylord Nelson, Secretary of State Dean Rusk, President Richard Nixon, and other ambassadors, dignitaries, and high-ranking officials. She met with former First Lady Mamie Eisenhower, and entertained prominent individuals such as Lady Astor, whom she met at the coronation of Queen Elizabeth II.
Geneva Valentine died in Washington, DC on April 10, 1971.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the correspondence, personal writings, resumes, address books, notes, meeting minutes, speeches, legal documents, tax files, financial records, reports, programs, memoranda, brochures, awards, certificates, magazines, newspaper clippings, photographs, yearbooks, scrapbooks, and travel memorabilia of Geneva K. Valentine and the organizations of which she was a part. The collection also contains records of some of Mrs. Valentine's family members, primarily her husband Hugh Valentine, Sr. and son Hugh Valentine, Jr. The bulk of the material dates from 1923-1987.The material in this collection covers Mrs. Valentine's history as a businesswoman, her contributions to the Washington, DC community in the areas of equal housing, alleviation of poverty, and crime prevention, and her advocacy at a national level for Civil Rights and desegregation.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into 6 series: Biographical information and personal materials; Photographs, yearbooks, and scrapbooks; Clubs and associations; Business and financial records; Community, political, and legislative engagement; and Family members of Geneva Valentine.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hugh Valentine, 2015 April 7 (2015.023)
Real property; Clubs -- Washington (D.C.); Citizens' associations; African Americans; Adams Morgan (Washington, D.C.); Photographs; Events; Civil rights; Housing; Urban renewal; Valentine, Hugh, Jr.; Valentine, Hugh, Jr.; Clinton and Valentine Development Company; Century Club; 2008 16th Street, Incorporated; National Urban League; Urban Coalition; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Leadership Conference on Civil Rights; Iota Phi Lambda Sorority; Western Union Telegraph Company; National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs; Asbury Methodist Church; Guy T.O. Hollyday House; Tidewater Developing Corporation; Adams-Morgan Federation; Equitable Realty Company; Orbital Properties, Incorporated; Arundel Ridge Corporation; Inspiration House; Positive Action Against Crime
- Biographical information and personal materials, 1923-1971; Series 1; 3 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  The materials of this series include biographical information about Geneva Valentine including two obituaries and a eulogy, as well as original works and writings she produced, such as poertry, memoir chapters, speeches, invention blueprints, resumes, and correspondence. This series also includes travel records from a trip to Nashville and a European tour for the coronation of Queen Elizabeth II, where Mrs. Valentine met with delegates and ambassadors and was interviewed by the BBC due to her role as National President of the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs. Additionally, this series contains magazines, recipes, hospitality and etiquette guides, newspaper clippings, address books, handwritten notes, awards, and certificates belonging to Geneva Valentine. The materials in this series range in date from circa 1923 to Mrs. Valentine's death in 1971, and have been arranged from most to least proximity to Mrs. Valentine. Publications have been arranged chronologically where possible.
  The chapters of Mrs. Valentine's memoir are accompanied by editorial commentary and estimates for publishing fees. Her memoir and poetry cover topics such as family history, personal heartbreak, religion, and professional struggles and successes. Her obituary suggests that these documents had been delivered to publishers but not yet printed at the time of her death.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by material type, chronologically where possible.
  - Eulogy and obituaries for Geneva Valentine, 1971; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memoir [1/3], ca. 1961-1967; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memoir [2/3], ca. 1957; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memoir [3/3], Undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Poems, 1923-1941; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speeches, 1948-1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invention, 1955; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Resumes, ca.1956-1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and documents [1/8], 1936-1953; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    General
    Contains photographs
  - Correspondence and documents [2/8], 1952-1960; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and documents [3/8], 1935-1954; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and documents [4/8], 1935-1968; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and documents [5/8], 1937-1956; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and documents [6/8], 1942-1962; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and documents [7/8], 1943-1964; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and documents [8/8], 1952-1976; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Handwritten notes and papers, non-correspondence, Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Address books [1/2], Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Address books [2/2], Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Travel records: Nashville and Europe [1/2], ca. 1953; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Travel records: Nashville and Europe [2/2], ca. 1953; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Magazines, recipes, etc. [1/2], 1943-1960; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Magazines, recipes, etc. [2/2], 1961-1971; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings [1/2], 1943-1970; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings [2/2], 1967-1970; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Awards and certificates, 1945-1971; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Certificate of Geneva Valentine's trip to Europe, 1953; Series 1 (Flat box 5, Item 2)
    This certificate has been ripped into two pieces and is crumpled to the point where it is impossible to open. Most likely needs preservation attention.
  - Certificate: A Tribute of Appreciation to The Business and Professional Women's League by the Washington Vicinity Federation of Women's Clubs of the National Association of Colored Women, 1948; Series 1 (Flat box 5, Item 3)
    May need preservation attention
  - Plaque: National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs Silver Anniversary Award, 1960; Series 1 (Flat box 5, Item 4)
  - Plaque: National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs National Sojourner Truth Meritorious Service Award, 1963; Series 1 (Flat box 5, Item 5)
- Photographs, yearbooks, and scrapbooks, 1922-2008; 1922-1967; Series 2; 5.5 Linear Feet
  Arranged by material type, chronologically.
  The materials in this series include photographs, scrapbooks, and yearbooks of Geneva Valentine, her family, her 1953 trip to Europe, and the organizations of which she was a part, including the Century Club and the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs. They range in date from Mrs. Valentine's 1922 high school yearbook through the 1960s, with one photograph from 2008 found in a scrapbook of materials pertaining to Hugh Valentine Jr. The series is organized such that scrapbooks, photo albums, the baby book of Geneva's daughter Jeanne, and other bound collections of photographs are first in the series, followed by individual images or smaller groups in roughly chronological order. This series also contains one folder of negatives, one folder of photocopied images, and several flat boxes of oversize scrapbooks and portraits.
  The images and ephemera in this series provide visual insight into areas of Mrs. Valentine's life and work, with subjects including the family and its cat, houses and construction, social and professional functions, honorees of awards, community spaces such as Inspiration House, and a photograph of Mrs. Valentine meeting former First Lady Mamie Eisenhower.
  - Family photo album, 1926-1930; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook [1/3], 1940-1963; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook [2/3], 1940-1956; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook [3/3], 1937-1947; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photo album, 1947, undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook: European travel and pre-departure correspondence [1/2], 1953-1954; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook: European travel and pre-departure correspondence [2/2], 1953; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook: European travel, 1953; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Century Club scrapbook [1/2], 1955-1968; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Century Club scrapbook [2/2], ca. 1952-1960; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook: Hugh Valentine Jr., 1954-2008; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Dunbar High School yearbook, 1922; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Baby book for Jeanne Valentine, 1927; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, ca. 1940s, 1942; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, ca. 1940s; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1943-1947; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, 1940s-1950s; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, ca.1950s-1960s; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, ca.1950s-1962; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Photographs: construction and houses, ca. 1958; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, ca.1960-1963; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Photographs for Pause and Acclaim event, 1963-1964; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of Eva Johnson, 1964; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and correspondence, 1969; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, Undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Photograph, Undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, Undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, Undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, Undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, Undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Photograph, Undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Photographs, Undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Negatives, Undated; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Photocopies of images, ca.1950s; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook: Equitable Realty Co. history, 1935-1947; Series 2 (Flat box 9, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook: National Association of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc., 1935; Series 2 (Flat box 10, Item 1)
    Leather album has red rot
  - Photographs, ca. 1940s-1950s; Series 2 (Flat box 11, Item 1)
  - Art Scrapbook, Undated; Series 2 (Flat box 11, Item 2)
  - Portrait of Geneva Valentine, Undated; Series 2 (Flat box 11, Item 3)
  - Scrapbook: Century Club, ca. 1941-1955; Series 2 (Flat box 12, Item 1)
- Clubs and associations, 1948-1970; Series 3; 2.25 Linear Feet
  The materials of this series include correspondence, minutes, speeches, newsletters, reports, publications, event planning documents, photographs, and membership records of the Century Club, the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs, and other social and professional organizations to which Geneva Valentine belonged, including the Iota Phi Lambda sorority. They primarily range in date from the 1940s through the 1970s, with some publications dating as late as 1984. The series is arranged alphabetically by organization where possible.
  In her role as National President of the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Mrs. Valentine traveled to Europe for the 1953 coronation of Queen Elizabeth II, and served as a delegate at the White House Conference on Aging in 1963. She has also been featured in multiple issues of Responsibility, the official magazine of the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs. Mrs. Valentine (and the organizations with which she was involved) planned and sponsored fundraisers and events that supported various community initiatives, including education and scholarships for young women.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Century Club documents [1/4], 1954-1957; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Century Club documents [2/4], 1954-1957; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Century Club Documents [3/4], 1955-1960; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Century Club documents [4/4], 1955-1958; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Century Club: minutes, speeches, newsletters, events, 1960-1970; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Century Club: membership and correspondence, 1964-1970; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Century Club: "Report on a Family Affair", 1963; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Century Club: photos, documents, correspondence [1/2], 1965-1970; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Century Club: photos, documents, correspondence [2/2], 1965-1970; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Century Club: printing plate of presidents, 1965; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Century Club: Founders Day 1965, Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Century Club: Founders Day 1967, Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs documents [1/2], 1968-1970; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs documents [2/2], 1968-1969; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs documents and correspondence [1/3], 1953-1970; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs documents and correspondence [2/3], 1966-1968; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs documents and correspondence [3/3], 1966-1968; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs: publications and flyers, 1951-1967; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs: Responsibility Magazine [1/2], 1944-1953; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs: Responsibility Magazine [2/2], 1953-1969; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs: conference publications and documents [1/3], 1951-1963; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs: conference publications and documents [2/3], 1963-1967; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs: conference publications and documents [3/3], 1967-1984; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs: travel materials (England) and delegate materials (White House Conference on Aging), 1953-1961; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs: minutes, memos, reports, 1948-1969; Series 3 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Other clubs and organizations: publications, correspondence [1/2], 1942-1970; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Other clubs and organizations: publications, correspondence [2/2], 1966-1967; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Business and financial records, 1939-1984; Series 4; 2.5 Linear Feet
  The materials of this series include correspondence, financial records, minutes, incorporation documents, deeds, leases, land survey maps, and other records pertaining to the real estate companies and other corporations Geneva Valentine and her immediate family members owned, managed, or substantially interacted with. These organizations include 2008 16th Street, Inc., the Arundel Ridge Corporation, the Clinton and Valentine Development Corporation, Equitable Realty Company, Orbital Properties, Inc., Tidewater Developing Corporation, Valentine Realty, Western Union, and Hamburger Grill. Some of these companies remained under family ownership after Mrs. Valentine's death, therefore the records in this series date from 1939 to 1987. This series also contains income tax records, financial documents, reports from Mrs. Valentine's time as a notary public, lawsuit documentation and statements, court summons, and other legal records of Geneva Valentine and other individuals.
  The materials for businesses in this series are arranged alphabetically by organization where possible, followed by financial documents arranged by proximity to Mrs. Valentine, and legal documents.
  Arranged alphabetically, then by subject.
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [1/10], 1949-1984; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [2/10], 1958-1979; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [3/10], 1968-1987; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [4/10], 1985-1987; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [5/10], 1985-1987; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [6/10], 1977-1978; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [7/10], 1961-1973; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [8/10], 1954-1978; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [9/10], 1970-1986; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - 2008 16th Street Inc. records [10/10], 1950-1967; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Arundel Ridge Corporation documents, 1955-1972; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Clinton and Valentine Development Corp. minutes and records, 1956-1959; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Equitable Realty Co. documents [1/6], 1939-1954; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Equitable Realty Co. documents [2/6], 1948-1973; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Equitable Realty Co. documents [3/6], 1949-1964; Series 4 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Equitable Realty Co. documents [4/6], 1950-1966; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Equitable Realty Co. documents [5/6], 1953-1972; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Equitable Realty Co. documents [6/6], 1962-1967; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Equitable Realty Co. minutes and incorporation records, 1959-1964; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Orbital Properties Inc. documents, 1968-1972; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Tidewater Developing Corp. documents, 1956-1961; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Valentine Realty documents, 1968-1970; Series 4 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Real estate and finance correspondence and publications, 1957-1970; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Corporations managed by Geneva Valentine, 1935-1962; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Financial documents of individuals: Geneva Valentine, 1953-1968; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Financial documents of individuals: outside Valentine family, 1959-1968; Series 4 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Legal documents, court-related materials, 1959-1968; Series 4 (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Community, political, and legislative engagement, 1948-1971; Series 5; 2.25 Linear Feet
  The materials of this series include correspondence, memoranda, newsletters, financial documents, meeting minutes, reports, publications, and event planning documents pertaining to Mrs. Valentine's involvement in Washington, DC community organizations as well as national political and legislative initiatives. This series ranges in date from 1948 to 1971and is arranged with community organizations first in alphabetical order where possible, followed by documents pertaining to national political and legislative initiatives. The community initiatives and organizations documented in this series include the Adams-Morgan Federation (of which Mrs. Valentine served as president until the time of her death), the Beautification Committee for Adams-Morgan, Asbury Methodist Church, the Guy T.O. Hollyday House, Inspiration House, Housing and Urban Development-related initiatives, Positive Action Against Crime (a group which Mrs. Valentine helped organize), the Mayor's Economic Development Committee, the Mary Church Terrell Fund, and Metrorail.
  Through her involvement with the Leadership Conference on Civil Rights, the Natinal Urban League, the Urban Coalition, the DC Women's Anti-Crime Crusade, and her position as Legislative Chairman of the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Mrs. Valentine advocated for anti-violence, alleviation of urban poverty, crime prevention, housing and education issues, as well as Civil Rights legislation and desegregation initiatives, and "Defense Against Communism," a subject about which Mrs. Valentine helped publish a fact sheet as part of her leadership in the Assembly of Women's Organizations for National Security. She also corresponded with organizations such as Planned Parenthood to work on health and family planning-related initiatives.